[Music]
hey folks
welcome to the dark horse podcast live
stream
i believe this is our 36th is that
correct that's right
36. that's hard to imagine i have to say
too
yeah it is hard to say harder that you
try it at home you'll see
um i'm sitting with dr heather heing as
always and we have
as always too much to discuss for the
allotted time
on account of it being 2020 and things
just keep
happening do they ever it's uh it's
almost too much to keep up with
um of course a lot going on uh today
and we will get to it in due course
where shall we start you wanted to start
with a
summary of the three big ideas that you
uh have been talking about in the last
couple of live streams and bring them
all together just to
remind us at the top of the hour
verificationism autoimmunity
and group psychosis right so these are
three concepts that i believe
are at least very useful if not
necessary
in cobbling together a mechanism for
sense making
in this moment where our sense making is
becoming increasingly deranged and in
fact the model
in part explains why sense making is
becoming
so deranged so i'm actually going to
start with autoimmunity
autoimmunity is a process by which
the body which is supposed to recognize
an absolute distinction
between molecules that you yourself make
and molecules that you yourself do not
make and therefore if they are
organic molecules the body assumes are
hostile and it attacks them with the
immune system
so that system develops when you're very
young
your system recognizes every molecule
that you
yourself are producing and it eliminates
the cells in your immune system that
react to it
leaving only cells that react to other
things
so this is a an analogy for the
situation that we find ourselves in
where we see many in our midst attacking
the very structures on which our system
depends
and they are attacking them with various
rationalizations claiming that these
structures are
so broken that they could not possibly
be rescued but the result is just like a
body that is
rejecting its own tissue that we are
putting ourselves in
mortal jeopardy as a result of this uh
misunderstanding i would also just as an
aside
point out that many of the food
sensitivities that some of us
have i have a very severe sensitivity to
wheat that these things are like
autoimmunity
except instead of reacting to your own
tissues you're reacting to foods
that you yourself consume so something
has caused me for example to become
reactive to wheat molecules when i eat
them my immune system reacts and i get
sick
as a result not of the wheat but as a
result of my reaction to it
so autoimmunity is a key concept
the second key concept for sense making
in this moment
is verificationism so verificationism is
a process whereby instead of trying to
find reasons to disbelieve
some hypothesis you look for reasons to
believe it
and the problem with verificationism is
that one
can often find some evidence for a wrong
idea and therefore if you are looking
for evidence that confirms a hypothesis
you will very often validate it even
though it is false
whereas if you try to falsify a
hypothesis
and you fail that means there isn't
strong evidence against it and the
hypothesis probably has a good
degree of truth in it so the claim is
that most of what people are doing as
they are trying to make sense of the
world at the moment
involves verificationism that they have
a perspective and they are looking for
things that validate it and they are
finding a tremendous amount of support
for wrong ideas on the basis that they
are looking only for those things that
support them rather than things
that negate them which results in
what we are arguing is group psychosis
that psychosis is essentially the result
of incompatible programs running
simultaneously that one one cannot
reconcile
two things or cannot find a mechanism to
compartmentalize them and keep them
apart
what happens is the programs keep
tripping over each other
and so one ends up responding to a
a view of reality that is um
false and disruptive of the ability to
to function properly so much of what we
see
is the result for example of two
perspectives
both of which are wrong being
simultaneously
deployed to different populations who
find each other increasingly
understandable
these incompatibilities are resulting in
us at some level
literally becoming crazy some of us as
individuals
but all of us as part of this group that
cannot figure out
even in what language to approach each
other to discuss what we face and what
our
overwhelmingly common interests clearly
are we can't figure out how to protect
them because
the incompatibilities between these
world views
are too great the gap is too big for us
to look past it
yeah in the language of sense making we
literally do not find any sense in those
who are on the other side
we do not find any sense and
increasingly we regard them as some
anomalous
phenomenon right in fact i would argue
that one of the
outgrowths of a psychotic collective
sense making
is the verificationist belief that in
fact you've got it right
and the other side is simply insane and
if one can for a moment just step out of
your own
sense-making bubble and realize that the
likelihood of that
is actually quite small right it's
certainly possible for a small number of
people
to be simply insane but the idea that
half the population has simply lost its
mind while you have retained a perfect
grasp of what's going on
is indeed quite unlikely so
the trick the thing which actually i
swear if you'll try it you'll find it
rewarding and maybe even reassuring but
the trick is to figure out
who you can talk to in that group of
people who you probably regard
as batshit crazy who might be able to
convey to you where to stand in order to
see through their eyes
now many on your own side will tell you
don't you dare
right to the extent that you even humor
them as if they are making some kind of
point you are putting
the thing that we must do right away in
jeopardy
and you must ignore that if your purpose
is to figure out what's going on rather
than just to simply participate on a
team
no matter how dangerous its viewpoint
has become then it is necessary that you
figure out how
to understand what those on the other
side are
seeing all right so that's the model and
indeed i think you will see in many of
the things that we discussed today that
these
these uh ways these concepts that help
organize
um our thinking around the way events
are unfolding in the world
many of them are manifest in these other
unrelated
topics or seemingly unrelated topics
well to your final point there i would
say that we hear
a lot from people who say they are right
of center uh who say they
enjoy hearing what we have to say
because we are
trying to make sense rather than simply
indoctrinate and there are a number of
ways that that
little little sound bite can sound but
um that people
are coming to us despite the fact that
we probably have never voted the same
way they have
or would disagree on a lot of the
methods by which we are trying to
obtain a just world
but that so long as we do share
underlying values which the vast
majority of us do
um that people are heartened
conservatives good faith conservatives
are heartened to hear us
as good faith liberals doing this kind
of analysis
and one of the things that is so
disheartening and i think we may um i
mean i guess we could start here but i
want to talk
just briefly at some point today about
um
about what's going on in louisville and
the response to it i mean maybe that is
the right way
i thought we would finish there but
should we maybe start there well i want
to
uh follow on two things maybe we can
come back to that
one is uh in somewhere in i think it
must have been at the end of last week i
happened to catch a tucker carlson
monologue
in which he specifically alerted his
audience he
called out honorable liberals who are
horrified by what's going on
on the nominal left at the moment and
his exact phrase was something like
you know honorable liberals are
horrified too
they exist you know right and he was
actually
calling out the very fact that it's easy
to misunderstand that
such a person on the other side might
exist and he is uh you know i felt a
little bit that he was
uh winking at us and some of uh our idw
friends who have managed to make uh
higher quality sense in these
confusing moments but the other thing we
get is the flip side
um which you called out in an early live
stream
uh which was the inverse
of trump derangement syndrome yes
and so the mirror image of trump dramir
image of trump derangement syndrome
which we often hear
too when we critique trump when we say
things like really he must be
removed from office right we must vote
him out
i don't feel like i'm saying anything
extraordinary in the context of
a democracy right the idea that a
sitting president has
demonstrated that they must be
eliminated in
the next round of elections is par for
the course and yet we are frequently
accused
of being just simply blinded by our
hatred for trump and i must say
i don't actually feel hatred i feel
urgency
right i feel like it's that critique is
exactly as
dumb as the response uh to trump
that he cannot do anything right and
therefore anything that comes out of his
mouth must be wrong
that is exactly as dumb frankly and
exactly as uh as
dangerous uh response you know every
person in any position
must be critiquable and uh ascribing to
someone who critiques
someone else uh a a you know derangement
syndrome as a way to get rid of their
critique
uh is you know it's schoolyard tactics
it's it's the antics of a third grader
really well so i want to you know
the the key question is can you escape
it whatever it is that drives you to
these things
and i feel a lot of people are just
being reflexive
and that the necessity at this moment
really the only hope i
see for us navigating this moment in
history and coming out
in any sort of decent shape whatsoever
is
the ability to look past the triggers
that other people have on their surface
in order to be able to partner with
others who
are overwhelmingly in agreement about
for example
values and so this is this is what
annoyed me so much about the harper's
letter was that
it took great pains to stick a finger in
the eye of conservatives rather than
partnering with the conservatives who
are clearly ready to play and
um so anyway we need to stop being so
triggered
people who uh believe something that is
incompatible with your worldview may
be many things that are compatible and
finding the way to bridge those
gaps is uh it is essential it is where
where hope exists and hence hence the
resonance of the concept of unity at the
moment
so to uh to this point and i don't think
we should spend much time here because
we have so many other things we want to
do
um it has been it has been reported
just a couple of places that what is
that something very very
bad is going on in louisville kentucky
so zach you can put up my screen and
actually keep it up while i
scroll through a couple of tabs the
louisville career journal which is the
local newspaper
reported on um i was updated
uh yesterday was reported first on
august 1st
uh that the cuban community plans rally
at the nulu restaurant in response to
black lives matter demands
and uh some of you will have heard what
what this story is but
um basically this guy fernando martinez
uh who is uh himself an immigrant from
cuba and has become successful as a
restaurant group
in louisville basically received what he
described as mafia tactics
shakedown requests from the local black
lives matter movement
and uh yeah they they were requiring
things like x percent of the purchases
be made from black owned businesses
and x percent of the employees be black
to reflect uh the underlying
demographics of
of louisville and you know this this is
sort of as we have come to expect at
least the two of us and many of
many people watching from the
uh we would like to think the fringe
parts of the black lives matter movement
but um
of course this these sorts of things are
described and to some degree celebrated
on the block on the official black lives
matter website
so once again black lives matter is not
what it seems just because it's wrapped
up in a bow with words that sound like
words we all should and need to be able
to get behind
doesn't mean that it is what it claims
to be so the courier journal reported
this
and uh fox picked it up
and uh used you know added a little bit
of reporting but mostly i think just
uh picked up picked up the story so i
we've been looking at this story for a
couple days here's the uh
um here's martinez the cuban restaurant
owner
with a statement um and you'll rather
than focus on oh my god here they go
again here goes black lives matter again
i thought i'd just look i was actually
hopeful so this morning at 11 30 a.m
our times just about an hour ago i just
went to
five of the major media outlets and
searched on louisville figuring that
anything else might be too you know to
fringe but i just searched on louisville
so when i searched on louisville after
this story has been in the news
that we are seeing for three days the
new york times
um its last louisville story is
from two days before um the louisville
paper first published this and um
in which louisville was declaring racism
a public health crisis so nothing there
wapo the washington post um sorry my
computer crashed just before airing
um just uh four days before
uh is uh louisville received an
extension to respond to ncaa allegations
so nothing there's something from longer
ago about the brianna taylor protest
nothing there cnn
again nothing we apparently have a polar
bear dying at a zoo
which you know it doesn't please me but
it has nothing to do with the actual
news that is coming out of louisville
uh here we have msnbc similarly
absolutely nothing about this story and
uh i went to time magazine as well and
again nothing so um that's just
i figure you could do this for almost
all of these stories and this was simple
because there was a city
where there have been protests there has
been action there has been reporting of
late
let's see if as soon as the narrative
switches
we get any play at all and apparently
the answer is no
so um i want to
take a little victory lap here for idw
style sense making because the story
clearly
reflects a pattern and i think
actually some of the uh demands were
even more onerous than the ones
that you reported yeah actually i might
be able to
don't switch to my thing here but um
you know uh non-profits in the newly
district will submit to a voluntary
external audit of their board of
trustees
and take necessary steps uh quarterly
roundtable discussions to be held
accountable for their commitments to
these demands all business owners and
non-profit leaders um
yeah and oh dr dress code policies if
the claim is dress code
policies inherently discriminate against
black folks within the transgender
community you must eliminate dress code
policies
and we will not waiver while the black
community continues to be destroyed
so some of them um i would just like to
point out
you just went through a series of
mainstream
uh press outlets that failed to report
the story entirely
um earliest uh prediction of such a
thing i would say
is eric's coining of the term
intersectional shakedown
which goes back years yep
um i have argued that and of course his
gin
gated in institutional narrative both of
those things right are resonant why
do you not see this because the gate has
closed and this narrative
um will not be breached by that
inconvenient fact
i have said that this movement is
interested in reparations
24 hours a day seven days a week 365
days a year
at every context in every scale every
interaction
right this is beginning to be that you
have pointed
to the proliferation
of things like black lives matter signs
in store windows that you have called uh
don't hurt me displays and i believe
that
michael tracy who to the point about
bridging divides with people michael
tracy who has tangled with
various people in the idw at various
points nonetheless put together
a report apparently where he goes
through he was on the ground here in
portland
and he released some very dramatic uh
video of him being
uh uh attacked by
uh antifa members but he apparently
shows what you and i know from being
downtown here in portland which is that
there is
yes the protests were concentrated
around the federal buildings but there's
damage
extensive and there are many businesses
that effectively plea
not to be injured on the basis that they
support
black lives matter and so what this all
does is a it makes it impossible to know
how much organic support there actually
is because there's a whole hell of a lot
of inorganic support that people
recognize that whether it's the question
of their personal reputations being
destroyed and their
livelihoods being wiped out or whether
it's the businesses that they have built
and their ability to continue to
function
in place you know we've seen years of
this kind of nonsense where
you know women were attacked for uh
making burritos while not being mexican
and um so anyway the point is
and this and this is all uh directly
predicted by the
hovel essay that i read from last time
exactly his green grocer his green
grocer who puts the sign in in his
window
um so if you're paying attention to the
mainstream sites
you will have no idea that this is even
going on you will not understand that
your sense making is
missing this very important piece of
information about what this movement is
and so when you see people like us
troubled by the idea that this movement
is
partnering with the democratic party and
what does that mean for the future of
the country
you'll think we're overreacting right
because you've been fed
a verificationist slate that will lead
you to believe that things aren't nearly
so troubling as they
actually are we are for instance to
believe that now the feds are out of
portland everything's fine
and of course what has happened is that
the uh
that the rioters have moved to the east
side of portland to
a local police precinct where they are
making trouble there they're no longer
in front of the federal building
they have they've moved their activities
so all those going to the federal
building and looking for confirmation
that it was the feds who were causing
this can find that that is the
verificationism in action
so it's like um willful blindness
using verificationism you will be
provided a set of evidence that is safe
for you to navigate and say i don't see
the problem
right and it's uh it's very very
dangerous yeah
um i guess one final point i would make
is something emerged
i believe yesterday body cam footage
from the george floyd arrest
and i must say back when i was on
uh joe rogan's program last when when
would that have been
june maybe july june july um somewhere
on the cusp of uh of the dawning of july
and i um one of the things i talked to
him about
was that the age of aquarius i'm not
sure
no that's a boomer thing i'm not into it
but um
anyway i talked to joe about the
troubling
hints that the george floyd arrest was a
very complex thing that would require a
court to sort out
the details which i still feel very
strange about saying
given what everybody seems to believe
about this arrest
in the intervening time a transcript
of the body cam footage emerged and i
read it as you did
and it is full of complexities that
reflect yes the need to actually sort
out
what the police policy was what the
state of george floyd was
lots of things including that he uh
insisted he couldn't breathe before he
ever hit the ground that he
actually um requested to be put on the
ground that he refused to be
put in the in the vehicle but in any
case the body cam footage emerged
yesterday and it does reflect the same
complexity that requires
sorting this out in a court
but then today cnn
released an edit of that video which
seems to strongly suggest the
alternative interpretation that
everything is exactly as you've been
told
it's just as dire as you think so are
you saying that was released yesterday
is unedited
that we have access that what was
released by the police department
presumably is unedited do we have reason
to believe that that's true
i am saying that first of all i'm not
sure what unedited it means there's
obviously a start and a stop point and
you've got
between the start and stop point are we
seeing everything that was recorded
um that's a good question i'd like to
know the answer to so an edit of an edit
is obviously devious but an edit of a
non-edit
is even is far more devious right and
here's what i would caution
our viewers i think you should see the
whole thing
and before you formulate a judgment on
what you've seen
you should look at all of it in context
if you assume
that cnn is presenting you with the
salient bits and you make
you formulate a judgment based on that i
think you will come out somewhere
very different than you would come out
if you just simply looked at whatever it
is
that the body cams recorded as they were
operating
so um this
you know incredibly uncomfortable to
talk about this but the complexity
of what unfolds is substantial and
you should not let anybody tell you what
it means
the answer is this does require a court
and in order to have a court
that functions properly it requires that
citizens who sit in that court as
members of a jury
understand that they are entitled to
reason based on evidence
rather than based on the threat of
violence that clearly exists if the
verdict does not go
the way the public expects and most of
the public
hopes it goes so um anyway it's a
caution
about verificationism and about the fact
that the gated institutional narrative
uh is inclined to deliver you something
that your verificationist mindset
is likely to accept and that this can
actually march us into
great danger uh of historical
proportions
okay should we move on to getting rid of
history and math oh
please yeah those are irritating yeah
all of us had some moments at least if
not
you know totally ridiculous classes so
let's just get rid of them yeah chalk on
the sleeves there's lots of things
that are very troubling about math yeah
okay zach would you show my screen here
uh this is actually uh reported by nbc
chicago area leaders call for illinois
to abolish history classes
his state rep lashon k ford said that
current history teachings overlook the
contributions of women and minorities
that may well be true but from that
starting point
he then says third paragraph here before
the um
ford asked the uh isboe and school
districts to immediately remove history
curriculum and books that quote
unfairly communicate history until quote
a suitable alternative is developed
he is asking for a change to the history
curriculum schools statewide and a
temporary halt
for all history instruction until an
alternative is decided upon
how is it that you think a new history
curriculum is going to be decided upon
i'll bet this guy gets to make some of
those decisions and maybe he even gets
to populate the committee that makes
those decisions
so zach you can you can take that down
now that's um
at some level more of the same defund
stem you know defund history that he
does not use the word defund but
we do have uh an academic uh
rochelle gutierrez uh who suggests in a
tweet i'm not gonna show it
but i will just read uh from it that we
should defund math
she is saying um sorry let me
pull it up so that i can see it um
i think that we should be literally
defunding math from k-12
k-12 curriculum requirements and testing
and
literally defunding math from society
parentheses stem funding and
salaries but also figuratively from our
minds parenthesis giving the current
version more value than other subjects
or gifts
so hat tip to james lindsay for bringing
this to light
uh he is as always on top of this stuff
um so i just i went and looked at who
this person is
um she's she's tenured it appears to be
at
one of the illinois state universities
and
um she has degrees in education not in
math
but her profile makes it look because
she is
interested in curriculum reform of math
that she's she's somehow involved that
she somehow has expertise in math
maths education she doesn't have any
degrees in math
she has degrees in education so
we have pointed out you can just show
this super briefly brett this is their
this is her cb this is her curriculum
vitae which is the
uh fancy resume for academics so yeah
she's at uh
illinois urbana-champaign um and wow she
got her
degree at university of chicago
important school but it's a school ahead
she got her phd in education and
curriculum and instruction
and she is um confusing
everyone who is listening to her into
thinking that someone who knows math
who does math who thinks in math thinks
also that we need to get math out of the
k
12 curriculum we then she expands a
little bit we need to get stem all of
stem
science tech uh engineering and math out
of um
salaries and like just basically start
defunding
all of all of stem but i think shutdown
stem was just for one day
yeah no it was except for it it was
except for
except for oh except for it was that was
the mod
the bailey was actually get rid of stem
that was the mod
that was the mod so you know one level
this is just
same old same old more of the same stuff
right but
the same moment that i saw this i also
was looking
at because i'm foolish enough still to
um subscribe to the hard copy of the
sunday new york times which you've been
suggesting we've dropped for
years now we don't even have a bird to
line the cage with no
we don't we don't but um the front page
of the sunday new york times this week
august
12th uh second oh god what month is it
oh my god
um it was headlined riding subway might
not pose an ordinate risk
so this is actually related to this mott
of
uh oh shut down stem for a day actually
we want to defund stem
so here we have show this for just
a moment while i read the first two
paragraphs here zack is the subway risky
it may be safer than you think
so slightly different headline than
what's in the hard copy which i just
showed you i have here
five months reads the beginning of the
article five months after the
coronavirus outbreak engulfed new york
city
riders are still staying away from
public transportation in enormous
numbers often because they are concerned
that sharing in closed places with
strangers
is simply too dangerous but the picture
emerging in major cities across the
world suggests that public
transportation may not be as risky as
nervous new yorkers believe
nervous new york nervous new yorkers
scared little new yorkers okay
give me my screen back thank you love um
nervous new yorkers simply too dangerous
uh
she uses the word the author uses the
word scared
later on find you will find in this
article buried
far deeper they buried the lead of
course
but not only did they bury the lead i
don't think the author and certainly not
the headline writer knows what the lead
is uh here's another quote from the
article which actually is accurate
once too many people pack onto a train
the ability to provide proper
ventilation diminishes significantly
when riders are standing shoulder to
shoulder any viral particles a sick
passenger exhales
could be readily inhaled by another
passenger even if both are wearing masks
so i'm going to put that into oh no i've
lost my
um i'm going to put that into
math speak biology speak this is this is
going to be a strategy
do you decide to go on the subway or not
that is density dependent
it is density dependent what you find in
this really long article that again was
the front
page of the sunday new york times this
week is
all sorts of you know we looked at we
looked at places worldwide and no one
has
been able to track outbreaks to subways
since the pandemic
has broken and they do mention that mit
article that found specific
um transmission risks on the new york
subway
and the one little nod to that is that
many people questioned its methodology
and there's no link i i can't see who
questioned its methodology i'm sure
people did but we talked about that
article in some depth back i don't even
know what episode
13 i'll make it up um something like
that uh and you know it looked it looked
good to us it was compelling but what
was the big difference
between the new york subway in march
versus now
there were many many many more people
riding on it and
nowhere in the world is mass transit
does mass transit have the ridership
that it did pre-pandemic
so a it is difficult to do track and
trace with
subway ridership because most people
aren't tracing their own movements that
way
and um and and it's just not being done
at that level
but even if it were even if the track
and trace data were fully reliable with
regard to subway ridership
it's not the same we expect exactly for
transmission of this virus to track with
density of the virus being transmitted
as droplets and aerosols impact spaces
and because
ridership is way down of course right of
course writing subways is going to be
safer which means
that this is actually uh a kind of
like journalistic medical malpractice
because the lead that they give is
actually guys you'd be a nervous
nellie's you're kind of scared you
should you should probably get back on
your subways now
well you know what if everyone takes
their advice suddenly the subways are
gonna get a lot more dangerous again
because they're going to be densely
packed again so let's
demonstrate this with the reducto ad
absurdum let's do it right at the point
that nobody is on the subway subways
become perfectly safe
try this rubric and you and would what
you see
and you know and okay there's an
economic imperative here right
subways need riders in order to to pay
their bills
and you know across the board every
sector in the economy
there's probably a few that are that are
growing right now but almost every
sector in the economy is failing as a
result of this pandemic and the
responses
to it and so presumably new york subway
needs
needs more riders in order to make
revenue but once they get more riders
they're going to be
it's going to be more dangerous place
for those writers and both of those
things need to be
in writer's heads when they are
receiving information especially from
so patently innumerate journalists as
this person is well i'm not even i mean
an enumerate journalist but it's serving
a larger function here
and i bet you that this is an analog for
what we went through with masks
where the idea is actually that's that's
where i'm going something has decided
that you need to believe that subways
are safe in order for new york to go
back to functioning because nobody's got
a plan b for what you do if people stop
riding the subways because they know
they're not safe right so this is gated
institutional narrative
which is now feeding you the following
pieces of information with which you can
use your verificationist model to get
back to riding the subway
what you need to know is yeah people
thought subways were dangerous you
probably heard that
the methodology of the study that said
that many people have questioned it
many people have questioned it so many
people right people on twitter
people at the supermarket um and uh my
five-year-old questioned that study
that's even more people yeah um so
anyway you've got
that study was questionable newer better
information you know
take the software update actually the
subway is much safer than you think
people who say otherwise are cowards
and lo and behold you're right in the
subway again when in fact you don't
need that study to tell you that the
subway is dangerous
right because what we know is that the
reason that the subway is dangerous
matches everything else we know right
it's
almost zero uv light environment it's
enclosed it has a circulation system
that is based on keeping people alive
with oxygen rather than
keeping the air purified this article
does
claim that the air circulation system on
the near
subway is uh is equipped to deal
with uh with viral particles i don't
know if that's true but it doesn't make
that claim right but it's a simple
question of rate which goes back to your
example about density dependence exactly
and that's i mean that's
that's that's why we tie it in here
right like we got people
right now who are making headway with
uh not just shut down stem for the day
but defund math
take math out of the schools take ma
take people who use
math out of the salaried faculty pool
and take it out of your everyday
assumption that it actually might be a
way of describing the universe that is
better than other ways of describing the
universe we've got people like that
making those claims at the same moment
that we've got the new york times
publishing yet another piece that
doesn't get a
you know it's not the simplest
mathematical concept density dependence
but it's not that hard and yet most
people
have probably never heard it in those in
those terms i mean everyone has actually
i think
an intuitive understanding of what it
means like you all everyone knows
that if they're trying to do their
grocery shopping quickly they should go
when they're
likely to be fewer people in the store
rather than more right that's a kind of
density dependent so everyone knows that
and probably everyone who remembers any
of their like high school biology will
remember
betsy and mimicry right in which you've
got a toxic
model organism that's just the language
of biology a toxic model
um which is out there paying the price
of having both
um the coloration to worn predators and
also the toxicity that will be the
punishment for predators should they
should they tangle with the model and
then you have a mimic species
um that is that looks like the model and
so pays the price of having to build
those colors and such
but doesn't have the toxin which is
itself a big metabolic cost like toxins
are expensive to
to make and to maintain and to carry
around and so the mimic
um it can be really really successful we
have like king snakes
mimicking coral snakes for instance and
you know there are many examples of this
and
we could we could spend hours talking
about this as we as we have in the past
um but for now let's just say that
probably when you learn this
in high school biology or even college
biology
um you weren't taught that
that strategy isn't simply good that
strategy
depends on the mimic being rare relative
to the model
because if predators are out there
looking
for food and they take a little taste
before they're old enough to know or
because they you know they're in a
species where they aren't taught by
their moms what to eat
they take a little taste first of the
brightly colored species
that happens to be the non-toxic one
then they're going to extrapolate that
they're all non-toxic and so the
non-toxic mimics need to be rare
relative to the toxic models in order
for this to work
that is density dependence and
guess what being safe on the subway
with a virus that transmits through
airborne particles is
density dependent masks don't inherently
make you safe whenever you wear them
right we're not we wouldn't be safer
right now wearing masks because we
lived together and have been in
isolation with each other and our two
kids since
march being outdoors not around other
people at this point in the current
evolution of this virus doesn't
it wouldn't make you safer to be wearing
a mask when you're indoors
with strangers yes you should be wearing
a mask it will make you safer because
the density of viral particles that you
are likely to run into
is higher so looting also fits a density
dependent model yes
you know looting when there's nobody
else looting and you will find yourself
under arrest if you do it when everybody
else is perfect
it's perfect yeah so anyway there's lots
of places where this concept
uh is useful and um yes it is totally
abused here in order to create a false
story i would point out also i believe
it was an mit study
that did the original work on the
subways and
one of the things that was really good
about it was it wasn't just like well
the data suggests it was subways
it actually drew a distinction between
local trains and express trains that
fit the model and the model was the
local trains are actually more dangerous
because you spend more time on them
which actually matches what we have
learned
about the way this virus transmits i
think well
i think it was impossible to know why
they were more dangerous and i think
there were two hypotheses both of which
seem right
right so it's you spend more time on
them if you're going from point a to
point d and you don't stop at b and c
you spend less time on an express
training
but but more people are going on and off
and therefore there's more opportunity
for transmission because there's a
greater chance that someone who's
infected has gotten on
and they're not mutually exclusive right
you get into a box and people are
exhaling virus if they have it into the
box and the box retains it even when the
person gets off
and more people are getting onto that
box and you're in contact with that air
for longer
you're going to get more virus so the
point is it wasn't even like
we don't know if that methodology was
any good the fact that that methodology
revealed
it's not that subways are dangerous
express trains are better local trains
are worse
that actually gives you a model for
transmission so this is high quality
work not low quality work
yes and for the new york times to take
up arms against it actually
matches what eric delivered in his most
recent intro essay
to his most recent portal podcast in
which he
builds a model one of the manifestations
of which is the headline is the story
right this is about optics and the idea
is what are you supposed to take away
from this
subways are safer than you think yeah
what happens don't be scared
you might get coveted you might give it
to somebody who's gonna die you might
end up
facing much longer term harms than you
otherwise uh would and so you know this
is
directly putting people in danger and
um if you're a devotee of the new york
times you won't know any better that's
right and i think it's also related to a
culture that i've been commenting on for
years
uh which is that it's it's sort of
widely considered in the intelligentsia
you know at like high-end cocktail
parties and the likes um
to be cool it's like cool or funny to be
enumerate
right to be like oh i suck at math or i
never did well in math
whereas obviously in the same circles if
you admitted that
you were illiterate you would not be
invited anymore right this this wouldn't
be acceptable and
you know the one sort of you know
partial carving out is you know people
who are dyslexic
can say like actually i really struggle
with that thing and you need
you're still forced to jump through
different and some of the same kind of
hoops in order to demonstrate
that you can do everything that us like
sort of fully literate folk are doing
and yet us fully numerate folk are not
even allowed to celebrate the fact that
we actually have a way
of understanding the world that is guess
what guys better
than the way that the enumerate folks
people
the the numerate people have of
understanding the world it is at least
an enumerate way of understanding the
world that allows for things like
density dependent transmission of viral
particles
will keep you alive for longer and safer
for longer than an enumerate way of
viewing the world
therefore it's better that's what better
means so better means
multiple things right that's one of the
things that better ends though
it also means testable reproducible
and so to both these issues here
um if we can step back to the question
of getting rid of history right getting
rid of history is clearly in favor of
some kind of
myth making which will fit some
narrative but
in order to fit a narrative rather than
fit what actually took place you have to
eliminate the possibility that a method
will tell you no that didn't happen
so witness the 1619 project
right it is at best well-intentioned
myth-making that is designed to
overwrite
history so that we don't have to deal
with its um
complexities but i think that's the most
generous interpretation possible
that's why i said best yep um but then
the other thing
let's look at this um this math educator
attacking math this is autoimmunity
yeah that's what this is this is the
system which knows how to think
quantitatively
attacking its ability to uh act
quantitatively and look
it's the same thing everywhere you've
got things that want
power for which the thing that stands in
their way is
like reality and the ability to detect
it and quantify it
want to get rid of math that's not
surprising if you want to re-uh
arrange well-being if you want to
redistribute it
and what stands in your way is the fact
that history doesn't reflect the story
that justifies
the redistribution right because it's
murkier than that
then you go after history and the point
is well we can just overwrite that with
something that does work
and what do you do if you want power and
the thing that stops you from taking
power over restaurant owners
is the police who show up and
you know arrest you for trying to extort
uh shop owners
well what do you do you demand the
abolition of the police
so it's attacking all of the structures
that make civilization work on the basis
that that gives somebody the ability to
do something they can't otherwise do
that we should absolutely be horrified
that they want to do yeah we need to
know what happened in history
we need to be able to quantify things be
able to test hypotheses
be able to establish the
counter-intuitive rather than just
assume that the intuitive and pleasant
is always
true that's not there's no way to
navigate you won't get very far you'll
you'll
you'll destroy yourself yep and i guess
i want to go back
uh just briefly to this point about a
mathematical understanding of
even your daily life is just a superior
one to an
an a mathematical and certainly to an
anti-mathematical understanding of daily
life
uh i want to make it clear that i
am totally recognizing that
most math education sucks so badly that
most people who are enumerate now
are not enumerate um through i won't say
any fault of their own necessarily but
many many people have been just betrayed
by an educational system that took their
mathematical their native mathematical
thinking away from them
so that's that's not fair that's
egregious that was a
you know massive failure of your
education if that happened to you and i
assume that it happened probably to a
majority of people watching even this
because
while uh we know that we have engineers
and scientists and such
among our viewers unless you have gone
into a science
and have continued to explicitly think
about math in your daily life
most people imagine that
because they didn't use it they lost it
or worse yet
they never had it at all because their
math teachers were terrible
they didn't understand math themselves
they used carrot and stick regimes to
motivate rather than oh my god this is
fun look at how much more empowered you
can be
in your own world and in the universe if
you just have
a few basic understandings of how math
works
and can employ those you know use them
and put them in your tool kit and use
them when they need to be used so
um one of the one of the reasons at this
point about math is going to be harder
to make i think is because
most most smart people even most smart
people who were paying attention
to this and who are sort of anti-woke
and really alarmed about what is going
on
right now in american society that's
spreading across the world
um know themselves to be
a bit enumerate know themselves to be a
bit scared of math and so
may not want to speak up for fear of
someone going oh yeah you know prove you
can do math
we don't need lots of people who can't
currently think mathematically to prove
it and you shouldn't be bullied
into accepting that you need to prove it
what you should
be is actually angry that this happened
to you if it did happen to you
and uh and be willing to learn your
concept like density dependence now
you've got it
and you know we could do a more complete
job of it but now you've got it and now
you know that actually
going on the subway is safe is an
incomplete rule that is inherently going
to be wrong at least sometimes and
therefore you shouldn't put that in your
in your quiver like that is not one of
the rules that you should be remembering
you should be thinking about
density dependence of viral particles is
is what i should be considering
as i decide whether or not i should go
into that situation at all and if i am
in that situation whether i should be
masked
et cetera i should also say much like
the situation
with uh the police
there's a lot to be said for the fact
that our math education mechanism
exactly as you're
suggesting here is broken enough to
disrupt most people's acquisition of the
stuff they need
and that we have tools at our disposal
that our ancestors did not
right so you know when a chalkboard was
your mechanism for conveying math you're
limited in a sense but we have all kinds
of tools that we could be leveraging
much more effectively you know you could
gamify the
acquisition of math so that it did not
feel like medicine that it felt like
fun and were we to do that my father did
with me
exactly and but here's the key why was
your father able to do that
because he deeply understood math right
most of the people teaching math do not
deeply understand math at best they're
competent at it yeah and the point is
our whole mechanism for education
suffers from the fact
that we don't budget to get the people
who are
liable to be insightful into the field
in order to teach children and this is
pennywise pound foolish because
you know if we had a mathematically
literate population how many more things
would we invent
how much more likely would we be to
be able to overcome this nonsense
narrative manufacture because people
would be able to detect the flaws
in what they were reading so you know
the cost we are paying
for not bringing the imaginative really
high quality mathematical minds into
teaching young people how to think about
math
is uh it's a giant loss and um
if you know we have immediate problems
but if we get past the immediate
problems
addressing that would be really high on
absolutely priorities because most the
way that math is taught is
often terrible and much of what is
taught
is um the wrong stuff right like i i
having now now being familiar with a lot
of the topics that are in the k12 math
curriculum because our kids
have been through it and are you know
advancing through it now um
it's clear that a lot of it is just oh
well this is this is in the textbook
that we've always used and so we're
going to force you to walk through this
and you know both of our kids happen to
have fun with math and i get to do with
them some of the same stuff my dad did
with me and
helping them out but but i still run
into stuff i'm like god i just don't
care like i just don't think this is
this is going to come up you know it
will come up
in a very particular place but math is
everywhere let's be teaching math
that reveals itself as everywhere
especially for the youngest ages
and then allow people to track into you
know what kind of do you think you're
feeling entrepreneurially you think
you're you know feeling engineer you're
like are you just want to be able to
interpret
the news that you're getting without
being duped by um either
are there bad actors or just people who
are bad at math all the time
and you know in some sense i think you
know i
certainly did not have an easy
relationship with my formal education at
all i mean
at no point but i remember
you do remember um but there's some you
know i do
feel educated somehow um
and i would say that as an educated
person uh you say math is everywhere
math is everywhere chemistry is
everywhere logic is everywhere right
physics is everywhere and the point is
you don't see to the deepest level
right you don't see the world through
the eyes of a theoretical physicist
unless you have very
good exposure but the ability to peer
into all of these levels you know when
we talk about immunity
you're talking about the chemistry at
the tip of something called an antibody
that you've all heard of but you don't
realize this is a y-shaped molecule
that has two pads on it that have
electromagnetic idiosyncrasies that
stick to some stuff and not other stuff
for reasons that you could demonstrate
with a child's magnets right and so the
ability to be able to see into these
puzzles it's not
that hard if somebody who knew what they
were doing
uh placed it in front of you in a way
that
is uh conducive to your acquiring it
it's effortless at some level
but if not then it's just a struggle
memorizing stuff from books that doesn't
stick because it doesn't
it's not connected to it you don't have
you you need to be able to build your
own architecture that makes sense to you
in your head and such that when you get
something new in your head you can even
when you when you receive some
information you're like oh this will fit
there and you know i feel this way very
explicitly about
um animals and you know ecology and
behavior and
you know when i'm when i'm in the
tropical rainforest and seeing yet
another bird
yet another interesting thing if i if i
have literally the phylogenic tree in my
head and go like oh
well um that's a woodpecker as opposed
to
a cuckoo as opposed to a tanager and i
know what you know woodpeckers tend to
do and oh that's something unusual for
woodpecker or
oh that fits right in it just gives you
an architecture right from the beginning
that you can
you can you can base things off of i
think
also what you just said makes me want to
give a shout out
to the model that was evergreen when it
worked
once again and i don't know that the
program in question did work but
you've heard this story when i was
flying out to my interview at evergreen
flipping through the at that point it
was still paper catalogs back in
would have been early 2002 i guess um
like the the catalog and these you know
full-time programs again where you often
had multiple faculty teaching
um from very different disciplines i
found a program
that really this this program was the
one that made me think ah
if you can do that there this is where i
want to be
teaching and therefore learning because
i will be learning from my co-faculty
and my students as well
it was called centering and it was about
the science and art of
pottery of ceramics and i had you know
over the last few years at that point
become a potter myself and was
fascinated
with exactly the artistic manifestations
of ceramic and i particularly liked will
thrown pottery
and of course the physics in wheel
thrown pottery is you know both obvious
and
intuitive which and you know we've
talked about this regard to frisbee as
well
um but also the chemistry like i i know
the least about chemistry of all of the
natural sciences probably but once you
are
mixing your own glazes and putting
pottery into sometimes an oxidation kiln
and sometimes a reduction kiln and
seeing the difference ways that say you
know copper reveals itself in an oxygen
and rich environment versus an
oxygen-reduced environment
is amazing and it just brings the at
least the science and physics to life
and you know i never dug my own clay but
you know you could do that and start to
think about some of the underlying
geology of biology too
and that's what this program allowed
like this it could have right the idea
of
learning how to make both hand-built and
wheel thrown uh
pottery and understanding the physics
and chemistry of it
in the same place at the same time with
the same faculty the same students
that's what what's an education can be
and um that's part of what that's part
of what we do mourn
at evergreen right i was just going to
add that
you also get issues of mathematical
scale with respect to the particle size
and the different kinds of clay and the
way that they
throw differently on a wheel yeah how
much thick this is
yeah porcelain versus uh a red
a red clay base um yeah i've not
forgotten all the all the various terms
because when we moved i had to
i had to give up my pottery studio um
that we had built
for me in our backyard um
but you know the diff the different
shrinkage right just you know some clay
bodies will shrink 15
some 25 and uh planning for it
and you know if you've done it throw and
it will shrink in some you know with
some kind of circularity to it and yeah
it's it's fascinating and remarkable and
it really does allow you to bring your
science and your art brain together
well most traditional education doesn't
let that happen because
in that case you've got a physical
product right there's also a reward
structure built into it which is really
the hidden key to
all education is that in general we sit
you in a chair and the reason that you
want to
learn the stuff is so that your teacher
doesn't say mean things that you
about you at the end of the term which
is not a good motivational structure
whereas
i want to get better at this because i
saw that right thing and i'd like to be
able to make one like it
um you know that's a very powerful
motivator so yes
figuring out how to get the motivation
in the right place is key
yeah i would also point out if i can
just go back to one other thing this
issue of
um we must unmake history and
mind you i think the history curriculum
sucks sure
yeah we must unmake the history
curriculum
because certain populations are
under-represented
in it really how do you know
right how do you know is a question that
is dependent on a method
which is dependent on mathematics so the
point is these two stories are in
conflict with each other
we must unmake the history curriculum
because
it is an error but the very claim that
it is in error about representation
implies that there is a method which
would with which we could figure out
what is now they've seen you coming it's
it's about your lived experience and
your personal emotional feeling about it
and that is what makes it true
right but then it's not that lived
experience and personal emotional
feelings about things aren't important
and real but it doesn't make things true
well but
but even then yeah like look i'll sign
up for that okay it's about lived
experience
who's right because which history
curriculum
is it everybody writes their own history
curriculum or is it
that the most aggrieved party gets the
right history for the world
or what exactly is this right no it's
it's it's that
and it's you know it's it's it's that
latter thing and
it is a an abuse of the idea of
anything about the collective being a
good thing
and it you know it's part of what makes
people so terrified of anything that
sounds like socialized anything you know
socialized medicine
or or um you know our education
sounds like this big boogeyman to a lot
of people on the right because they've
seen what thinking in terms of the
collective can do but you know
my favorite example of yours is the um
the fire department
oh yeah we have socialized fire
departments and good good for us
yeah i mean we didn't always right yeah
we do you know it used to be
i think there's a roman example where
they used to negotiate with you
uh you know and you'd pay more and more
to get them to put out your house as it
burned down because
something might be salvaged and then of
course there's a colonial version in
which
you had private fire departments and you
had to have a badge
there's like a little metal badge you
had to have on your building or the fire
department wouldn't lift a finger to
help you
and so we dealt with that problem and we
socialized the cost
and it's a risk pool and it makes
perfect sense and some things work this
way and some don't but
yep but anyways well that's and that and
that's key right some things work this
way and some things don't
i'm not saying that every you know
everything should not be socialized
and socialized can go very very badly
but look to the fire department for an
example of how this works and how it's
patently better than the other options
that have been tried
right so final cap on this i would say
is if you do not take a verificationist
approach
and if you simply even a sign up for
their epistemology and just see how far
you can push it before it breaks down
it breaks down almost instantly right so
the
example of you know if it's lived
experience whose lived experience is
who's that's going to tell us what we
must do what we must say what we must
accept
the fact that these things can't even go
two steps without contradicting
themselves or revealing
their absurdity is evidence that in some
sense instead of saying yes i'm on board
black lives matter
the answer is um actually
you don't have a clue how things work do
you right you're telling us that much
yeah and the idea that you want to
reformulate civilization
including education and journalism and
everything else
right tech sector the tech sector
policing all of these things
um and you are simultaneously telling us
that on any
posi any question on which we are
entitled to
investigate it turns out you're in error
and crazy
should say well okay okay you have the
psychosis maybe it is our responsibility
to help you with that but it is
certainly not our responsibility to put
you in charge
right that's not a good idea it is in
fact our responsibility to not let you
be in charge yes that that is what is in
fact our responsibility it is in fact
our responsibility
to you not to put you in charge not just
the rest of it right the fact that
you may be uh of a mind
that the plane is being piloted by
demons and that everybody else on the
plane is a demon and that you are the
only person who isn't possessed and
therefore you're the best
hope of landing it doesn't make it true
and we have an obligation to you
not to put you in the cockpit right so
that is where we are okay well we got a
lot more we want to talk about we're
coming up in an hour
um lots of things in coveted space um
and i know you wanted to at least get to
talking about the testing regime
yeah maybe i'll just introduce this so i
went through a situation
where about a week ago no a little more
than a week ago
i had a headache that had no explanation
and i was concerned that i might have
coveted um and it was plausible that i
would have contacted it though i don't
know of anybody
but anyway it revealed to me something
that i think
is a reflected in many people's
experience and b that is really
significant and um pretty scary
so i didn't think there was a high
chance i had cove but i thought there
might be a five percent chance that i
had coveted
but in light of that i know that if i
did have covid i would go to extreme
lengths
to protect my family from getting it you
know if it came down to it
i would uh you know if i had a trailer
i'd live in it if i had to i'd rent a
room somewhere and isolate myself
and you know i'd be very careful not to
give it to anybody who came to the door
but i would
you know order food or whatever i had to
do so i wasn't contacting
the world would be the right thing to do
but what i found
was a okay you think there's a five
percent chance you have coveted
you need a test okay so i went to get
the test
i got put through a rigmarole to get
the test which was bewildering i got the
stupidest medical advice you can imagine
i was told simultaneously
that i didn't need to worry about kovid
because i had been misled by the press
to think it was common
and then i was told if i had it there
would be no way to protect my family
from getting it too
is that the same person same person told
me that inside of three sentences of
each other
um so that was an official medical
consultation
then they didn't know what test they
were giving i said is this the pcr test
oh we don't know
really you don't know if it's the pcr
can you find out can you look it up do
you have the
the white paper that comes with the damn
test um well i did find out it was the
the paper the pcr test um but anyway i
went
i got the swab and then i waited and i
waited and i waited for a result
right and while i waited i was in the
situation do i assume
that i do have it in which case should i
be at a hotel
while i'm waiting for this test that
doesn't make any sense on the other hand
it doesn't make any sense not to do that
so i was caught in a middle ground that
i know is stupid which is i was wearing
a mask
in the house right all the time but i
wasn't insisting that you guys wear
masks which probably if i did have covid
would be the minimum thing necessary
right i left all the windows open so we
had air flow i spent as much time
outside as i could but the point is the
limit of what you can do if you think
there's a five percent chance you've got
it
is very different than what you should
do if you actually
do have it and it was a completely
incoherent
response and i have a sense that what
other people isn't that the word that
more than anything else describes
the the collective response to this
virus incoherent incoherent yeah
absolutely incoherent and then
ultimately
i did get my test results back they were
negative
but it doesn't mean that much why
because well but before you explain then
i mean this is super important but
um really you had none of the other
symptoms and they disappeared quickly
and so
in concert with a negative result it
seems it seems likely that that is an
accurate negative result
however yeah i mean i took my
temperature daily it never went up so i
had no other symptoms
the headache went away i never figured
out what it was about but
probably just a stray headache but the
point is okay i get my result
and then i start looking into its false
negative rate
and its false negative rate is through
the roof and it varies widely depending
upon how many days into symptoms
you actually had the test taken because
guess what
its efficacy is density dependent right
it's exactly
and so anyway my point is i think first
of all every i just coughed during this
little chat that is plausibly the first
cough
of a uh covid
uh set of symptoms right but almost
certainly not
right at the point that you cough do you
take action
right so we've been handed a well you
don't want to give other people covet
thing
but we have not been handed good tools
with which to know if we have it
or to trigger the top level action that
you would want to take if you did have
it
and my guess is almost everybody is
navigating this badly
almost everybody is probably
rationalizing to themselves
that i must not have it until it's way
too late
at which point um there's a less they
can you know do we know
about how much covid is responsive to
our behavior in other words the
difference between a case that is quick
to
go away in one of these cases that gives
people symptoms for
months down the road i haven't seen
those data if i haven't seen them
and aren't they i mean they they would
be relatively easy to collect and
there's some that would be the most
interesting and important for those of
us who could actually make sense of
okay given that i can't trust the
the collaborations of data that we're
seeing thrown at us
i'd like to be able to make my own
assessment right yeah does does
laying low if if you think you've got it
um
have a an impact on the course of the
disease i think it almost certainly has
to but i don't think
i don't think the data are out there at
least not available and the fact that
you and i are
even if they are the fact that you and i
looking at all the places that we do
look
are unaware of what the advice would be
about how to keep a case mild
if such advice exists at all the fact
that you
don't have a test that's worth a damn
and therefore
you know lots of people are uh getting
false negatives who are positive and
then
acting in presumably reckless ways as a
result of it
the whole thing is setting us up for
failure that's the point
yes we are being set up not only for
personal sometimes catastrophic medical
failure physiological failure by our
lack of information but we are being set
up for epidemiological failure on the
basis
that the data is too slow to emerge it's
too low quality
and the advice on what you're supposed
to do is anecdotal at best
so lots of the answer is lots and lots
of people are dying and as much as this
disease isn't as
deadly as we feared it is potentially
much more
destructive so every time you hear
oh it's not that serious because the
death rate
per infection is low you should ask the
question
okay but how much quality of life is
being lost by people who
recover or somewhat recover um because
the uh the stuff i'm reading is
certainly very frightening on that front
yeah no absolutely and here actually if
you want to show this sack um
here's just a it's a science news
article so it's published in
you know one of the top tier science
journals in the world
but it's one of these news articles uh
from brain fog to heart damage
copenhagen's lingering problems alarm
scientists
it starts with an extended anecdote
about
a neuroscientist who is 38 and has her
own lab at university college london
but who having quote unquote survived
covid finds herself still with
sufficient
both uh anatomical and physiological
symptoms in terms of joint and muscle
pain
but also um neurological symptoms
um like she is
she she says she has brain fog and
such that she cannot do the work that
she is accustomed to doing
and that this is uh now i think months
oh it says she said just three weeks
since march when her body temperature
was normal
so she's not dead therefore she doesn't
count as one of the deaths
and this is it's it's a terrible way of
assessing the impact of a disease right
deaths versus not deaths well this this
woman's career may
be over maybe over and we also don't
know she's young
she's in her 30s right we also don't
know you know
as we've discussed models of senescence
and the force that pulls you towards the
grave
we don't know how much life has been
lost the fact that you die from the
initial infection
is one thing but if you've had 15 years
knocked off your life that's not an
insignificant fact
so how many lives versus how much life
it's a different way of counting it's
both
counting but it's it's just a tiny bit
more nuance it's just a little bit more
uh categorization that is required to
imagine sort of
actuarially how you know what was your
expected life
uh life expectancy um and you know in 50
years
we might be able to know right but it
would it's it's going to be
such noisy data that we might never be
able to know but
of people who tested positive and had
cases that were serious enough to be
noted um do they
live less time than uh are expected by
uh life expectancy tables yeah and the
prediction is that they will
although again that's only counting just
actual you know
number of amount of moments lived as
opposed to quality of life
right and the quality of life thing you
know it's very hard to tell from the
reports the reports are frightening of
what people experience
yeah but um there is
you know basically people are having an
attack on the tissues across their body
which gives a huge diversity of symptoms
i'm also hearing about the recurrence of
these symptoms i have one friend who
has a pattern where he had it months ago
and he recovered
and every month it recurs
and the pattern is that the degree of
severity
decreases over time this is one person i
consider him highly reliable in terms of
the pattern he's experiencing but the
point is
the diversity is way too high to even
know how to count the damage here
yeah and that maybe just one more thing
quickly before we
we finish for this top hour um
that is part of what prompted a bunch of
uh
scientists uh to uh
create their own vaccine so this is
published in mit technology review
which is a very highly regarded
publication
and the headline is for those listing
and not watching some scientists are
taking a diy coronavirus vaccine
and nobody knows if it's legal or if it
works
okay fair enough um it's
the you know the story goes on this is
their site here
um they are calling themselves the rapid
deployment vaccine collaborative
and there's you know it's it's it's
fascinating there's there's a bunch of
good stuff here about what they're doing
what they're trying to do what they are
not promising
um but their basic point is
we don't foresee a a
valid reliable vaccine coming anytime
soon and given that and given how much
we're seeing
about yes pretty low death rate but
really high collateral damage rate from
this virus
we are going to prioritize uh creating a
vaccine for ourselves
and so they're doing it's it's kind of
citizen science by scientists
yeah george church is a big name
exactly so very important person um you
know neither of us has we we just came
uh became aware of this you know like a
half an hour or so before the podcast so
we have not
fully voted this but i guess one
question that shows up is
um you just what do you think like
should citizen scientists
even be allowed to
with tools that they have access to
because some of them have research labs
create their own um you know taking full
responsibility
for what happens if it doesn't go right
their own vaccines at home and you know
my first response is yeah
well yes and no it's my response now it
happens i'm reading here
what their mechanism is and basically
it's a synthetic peptide
they say these peptides are small
synthetically produced
portions of viral sequence now
what this means is that they are
delivering
proteins which are matches
for proteins produced by the virus
and therefore what they are doing is
they are triggering
the immune system to react to
antigens that the virus itself produces
so that when the virus shows up your
immune system recognizes ahead of time
now that strikes me
as much more likely to be safe
than the alternative which is to produce
an inactive virus
which therefore informs the immune
system by actually
diversifying in your system and
spreading antigens by
a mechanism that doesn't make you sick
but does infect
cells yeah now it's likely that or or
the third case is to kill off a virus or
inactivate it so that your immune system
just sees those particles itself
right and they say here also that you
know the antigen portion that they've
chosen could be substituted by others
for example the example they give is the
recombinant series cov2 spike
rbd and that you know for me what that
calls up
is okay well uh the efficacy of this
or really any other vaccine and they say
two this doesn't have to be for this
you know you could use this mechanism
this kind of
this framework um with other antigens
from other viruses
to make vaccines for other viruses
that is likely to be highly different in
efficacy
depending on which particular antigen
you use and it's going to be difficult
to predict in advance which antigen
is most likely to produce the
appropriate response in your own body
right but let's put it this way this is
potentially a good idea
the fact that they are not using virus
decreases
presumably to zero the chances of a
recombination event
in forming the virus of something it
doesn't yet know
the actual virus so peptides
probably good choice however the problem
is
you're you're playing with the
information that the immune system
uses to understand what antagonists it
is encountering
and so the possibility exists for
example to trigger an autoimmunity
by leading so you've got selection
inside the body functioning
to train the virus to be invisible to
immune systems that means the closer it
gets to self
the harder it is for the immune system
to fight so it's a go-to strategy it's
part of you know aids basically
uh hiv digs a hole in the immune system
which it then disappears into more or
less
that's that's what an autoimmune disease
means that it tricks your body into
thinking it's you
so that your own body doesn't go after
it well no an autoimmune disease let's
say that a virus oh i'm sorry i'm sorry
a virus
mimics your own particle yes and then
the immune system chases it
and it starts reacting to stuff that's
ever closer to you and then sooner or
later it's attacking
you know your own tissue like uh
cartilaginous tissue and uh
rheumatoid arthritis for example right i
misspoke yes
but but the point is if you're i'm not
saying this isn't worth it in this case
i
share the authors of that paper's fear
about the
danger with covet and the necessity to
do something
but in general do we want people messing
around with informing immune systems
you know based on these things there's a
there's a big hazard here so the
point is we really ought to be having
a proper discussion about the costs
risks and benefits of allowing this sort
of
behavior and the problem is we can't do
it in an environment
where the new york times is telling
people that subways are probably safe
and
uh you know uh the who is telling us
that masks don't work and all of this
stuff
that's clearly cooked up for reasons
that have nothing to do with our
actually being informed so anyway
yep very important problem to be solved
all right i think we're i think we're
there i think we have arrived
yeah so um
we will be taking your super chat
questions in the next hour um starting
in about 15 minutes
and we encourage you to if you have
questions either ask them at the very
end of this hour we'll be taking
from this hour in monitor monetary order
and next hour in the order in which they
come in
uh you can get access to a private q a
that we'll do every month at my patreon
and either of our patreons
access a private discord server for
people who are interested in these kinds
of conversations
um i promised a unity update and there
is one
the long-awaited unity campfire is going
to be deployed
tomorrow with a special guest i think
you will be
very pleased to see join our ranks um
we are likely to do this at six
o'clock pacific that is nine pm
eastern so that we can get everybody
able to watch live so
please tune in to our channel to find
that announcement the unity channel the
unity channel you can find that at
articles of unity
at articles of unity on twitter um you
can
also follow me on twitter
at brett weinstein bret has one t um in
any case please join us for that it
should be great
um we failed to mention what take took
place
in uh beirut this morning sorry for that
i know i promised it on twitter but we
just ran out of time
um so in any case if you're not aware of
what's going on
it's worth looking into we will see you
in 15
minutes all right be well everyone
you